All right, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף *daf* is ה *He*,
five. We pick up at the bottom of ד' עמוד ב' *Dalet
Amud Bet* and we get to a finally, well, we're going to
get back to the egg in a minute but we're going to
focus on a very different conceptual issue which is fascinating conceptually and
practically. So we pick up on ד' עמוד ב' *Dalet Amud Bet*
which starts איתמר *itmar* which is three lines before the lines get
wide. It starts with the words מקלעא ליה איסורא *mikla lei issura*.
איתמר *itmar*, it was taught: שני ימים טובים shenei yamim tovim. של
גליות *shnei yamim tovim shel galuyos*. You have two days, the two
day יום טוב Yom Tov. *yom tov* of... what's...
what's the status? In terms of... now again this is in the
context of the egg but you'll see it will raise a broader
question. רב Rav אמר נולדה בזה מותרת בזה *Rav amar nolda b'zeh
muteres b'zeh*: if the egg is born on one day יום טוב
Yom Tov, *yom tov*, it's permitted on the second day יום טוב
Yom Tov, *yom tov*. רב Rav אשי אמר נולדה בזה אסורה בזה
*Rav Ashi amar nolda b'zeh asura b'zeh*: if it's born on the
first day of יום טוב Yom Tov *yom tov*, it's forbidden on
the second day of יום טוב Yom Tov *yom tov*. So what's
this about? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לימא *leima* let's say
קסבר רב Rav אשי קדושה אחת kedusha achas. היא *kasavar Rav Ashi
kedusha achas hee*. רב Rav אשי *Rav Ashi* who says if it's
born on day one it's forbidden on day two, it's because he
holds that this is all one continuous קדושה kedusha. *kedusha*. Meaning the
normal way we would approach two days יום טוב Yom Tov. *yom
tov* and we know there are classic משניות Mishnayot *mishnayot* that deal
with this, is,
is that you don't know if today is יום טוב Yom Tov.
*yom tov* or if tomorrow is יום טוב Yom Tov *yom tov*.
I mean sort of we pretend as if. The idea of the
two day יום טוב Yom Tov. *yom tov* is the period when
they didn't know which day was the first day because of which
day was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*. So therefore if it's
born on one day, it could be permissible on the second because
it's born on the first, the first is יום טוב Yom Tov.
*yom tov* so then the second is חול *chol*, or if the
first was חול *chol* then it was born on חול *chol* and
it's permissible on יום טוב Yom Tov, *yom tov*. Even if you
consider like an earlier discussion we had before about ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah? *Rosh Hashanah* that they're both going to be treated as יום
טוב Yom Tov? *yom tov*, but as long as they're independent from
one another, so by the time you get to day two of
יום טוב Yom Tov. *yom tov*, the מוקצה *muktzah* considerations of day
two is a question of was it already born when day two
began and the answer is yes. So all of the logic would
dictate that if it's born on day one, it should be permissible
on day two. The only logic to say not is to treat
them as one continuous unit of קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* and then it's
like it was born on the middle in the middle of יום
טוב Yom Tov, *yom tov*. So born on the middle of day
one of יום טוב Yom Tov? *yom tov* it's forbidden for the
whole day one, so born on day one it's forbidden on day
two if you consider that to be one unit of קדושה kedusha?
*kedusha*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that seems to be רב
Rav אשי's *Rav Ashi's* position. והא *v'ha* but that can't be, דהא
רב Rav אשי מבדיל מיומא טבא לחבריה *deha Rav Ashi mavdil miyoma
tava lachavrei*. רב אשי *Rav Ashi* makes הבדלה *havdalah* from the first
day יום טוב Yom Tov. *yom tov* to the second. So if
he makes הבדלה *havdalah* you're considering the second day יום טוב Yom
Tov. *yom tov* to be distinct. Now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says he
would even say המבדיל בין קודש לחול *hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol*, which
is quite fascinating, which means okay I'll play along with the second
day יום טוב Yom Tov. *yom tov* and I won't do מלאכה
Melacha, *melacha*, I guess I'll have a סדר *seder* but bottom line
is I consider it חול *chol* and he would actually say המבדיל
בין קודש לחול *hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol*. Now you could have suggested
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* maybe it said המבדיל בין קודש לקודש
*hamavdil bein kodesh l'kodesh*, but whatever he did he clearly understood that
there was a distinct, you know, made a distinction between day one
and day two and that they were not one continuous unit. So
if that's true why isn't the egg permissible on day two? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, no ספוקא מספקא
ליה *safoka mesafeka lei*. Here's how we explain רב אשי *Rav Ashi*.
He's not certain how to deal with the two days of יום
טוב Yom Tov *yom tov* so he has a doubt. הכא לחומרא
והכא לחומרא *hacha l'chumra v'hacha l'chumra*. He says should I treat it
as one continuous קדושה kedusha. *kedusha*? Fine, that's one possibility and therefore
I'll forbid the egg that was born on day one on day
two. Maybe it's one continuous. On the other hand maybe it's two
separate קדושות kedushot. *kedushot* or it's a קדושה kedusha *kedusha* and a
חול *chol* and therefore I'll make הבדלה *havdalah* between day one and
day two. So that's, both positions are a מחמיר *machmir* position and
that's why he could hold contradictory, he's playing it safe. Of course
how do you make a ברכה *bracha* if you have a doubt?
Maybe you know maybe he did הבדלה *havdalah* without saying the ברכות
*brachot*, just said המבדיל בין קודש לחול *hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol* or
בין קודש לקודש *bein kodesh l'kodesh*, but that's how the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* explains רב אשי *Rav Ashi*. Okay so we're still consistent though
that the idea that the egg born on day one is forbidden
on day two is based on a on conceiving the two days
as one continuous קדושה Kedusha. *kedusha* as opposed to רב *Rav* who
would say they were two קדושות kedushot *kedushot*. So now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this, so now we're going to try to
work that out, one קדושה Kedusha *kedusha* or two קדושות kedushot. *kedushot*?
So אמר רב זירא *amar Rav Zeira*, so says רב זירא *Rav
Zeira*, I'm very sorry about the not enough גמרות Gemaras *Gemaras* here.
I don't know what happened to them.
אמר רב זירא *amar Rav Zeira*... okay good. אמר רב זירא *amar
Rav Zeira*... כוותיה דרב אשי מסתברא *k'vasei de'Rav Ashi mistabra*. You know
what רב אשי's *Rav Ashi's* position of one קדושה Kedusha *kedusha* makes
sense. Why? Let's hear this. דהשתא ידעינן בקביעא דירחא *de'hashtan yedinan b'keviya
d'yarcha*. Nowadays let's face it we know when the ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* was established. It's all based on a calendar that
we've predetermined and we know exactly when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
*Rosh Chodesh* is. Okay. וקא עבדינן תרי יומי *v'ka avdinan trei yomei*.
And nevertheless we do two days
יום טוב Yom Tov *yom tov*. So what's the logic? How do
you explain we do two
days? if we're doing it because not out of doubt. He says
there's no doubt nowadays. The only reason we do it is because
that's sort of the Rabbis established you keep two days in חוץ
לארץ. Chutz La'aretz So therefore it's all unified, it's become a two-day
יום טוב. Yom Tov If there's a doubt, is it today, is
it tomorrow, that gives them each separate weight. But if it's just
the Rabbis telling us keep two days יום טוב, Yom Tov. so
they all have the same weight. Now it's not obviously one's biblical,
one's rabbinic, but it's one unit. Okay, 'cause bottom line is we
don't really have a doubt. That's his position. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
אביי Abaye says no, כוותיה דרב מסתברא, k'vatai d'Rav mistabra, רב'ס Rav's
position of two separate sanctity of two independent days is the one
that makes more sense. Why? תנן, Tnan, we learn in a משנה.
Mishnah. בראשונה היו משיאין משואות, Barishona hayu masin masa'ot,
originally they had a great way of communicating
to חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. was established
in a way that everybody would know in time for יום טוב,
Yom Tov, which is what? They would have they would light things
they'd light bonfires on the tops of mountain tops and they'd have
them spaced equally and it would sort of be in a one
the next mountain top would see the bonfire and light its bonfire
and then the next one would see the bonfire and light its
you know so it would it would communicate very quickly over an
extremely long distance. That was how they used to do it and
everybody would know when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, was. But משקלקלו הכותים,
mishe'kilkalu ha'Kutim, presumably
משקלקלו המינים, mishe'kilkalu ha'minim, when the I assume that that does anybody
have a Steinsaltz no does he say המינים ha'minim or הכותים? ha'Kutim?
No, that's whatever, that's the ArtScroll anyway. Okay, but when the heretics,
you know, when the, you know, got made trouble or according to
this the Samaritans made trouble and they basically started lighting the bonfires
on the wrong day. Now it wasn't just to give the Rabbis
a hard time. It had to do with the debate about how
to set the calendar. And particularly according you know the Book of
the Jubilees we know from from the from the Second Temple literature
had a whole separate way of you know establishing the calendar. There's
basically also concern about how do you interpret the verse and this
was with the Sadducees that שבועות Shavuot is fifty days ממחרת השבת.
Mimacharat haShabbat. Is it literally שבת Shabbat or is it פסח? Pesach?
So a good way to have it all work out is to
ensure that the first day of פסח Pesach is שבת Shabbat and
then you sort of get it all worked out. So anyway they
would try to manipulate the calendar. So that's why this was not
working because you can't tell whose bonfire it is. So they're trying
to manipulate the calendar. They had to find a different way. התקינו
שיהיו שלוחים יוצאין. hitkinu she'yihyu shluchim yotzin. They had שלוחים shluchim of
בית דין Beit Din being sent out and maybe they came with
like an ID, so therefore you know exactly what the official day
of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh was. But that took a lot more
time. Okay, and that's why there became doubts in חוץ לארץ Chutz
La'aretz because it took a long time to find out and יום
טוב Yom Tov would come along and you still wouldn't know which
day was ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh So now that's the that's the
משנה. Mishnah. Now now אביי Abaye reflects on this. ואילו בטלו כותים,
v'ilu bitlu Kutim, let's assume that there were no longer the problem
with the כותים Kutim or the מינים minim and so on. There
was no longer that problem and we could go back to the
fires. עבדינן חד יומא, adinan chad yoma, then we would do one
day in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz because then the message would get
out quickly and we would only have to do one day. Or
another another hypothetical scenario עבדינן
חד יומא. adinan chad yoma. והיכא דמטו שלוחים, v'heicha d'matu shluchim, let's
take a one that's true even nowadays. Areas near Israel where the
שלוחים shluchim could get within two weeks of ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh,
so those areas which always knew in time for סוכות Sukkot and
in time for פסח Pesach when when the יום טוב Yom Tov.
began, those areas עבדינן חד יומא, adinan chad yoma, only do one
day. Okay, so now what is how does this all relevant to
is it a two-day יום yom is it one unit or two
units? So the way רש"י Rashi explains it is very simply. He
says look, and this by the way is the question of how
to conceptualize two days יום טוב. Yom Tov Because some גמרות
sort of refer to it as a מנהג, minhag, you know, מנהג
אבותינו בידינו, minhag avoteinu b'yadeinu, and that's why we keep it. We
keep the practice that was established. But others refer to it as
a תקנה, takana, like חז"ל Chazal established a two-day that we have
to keep the second day. Well which is it? Is it a
practice that we're maintaining or is it a תקנה? takana? That's actually
what רש"י Rashi. says is being debated here. One approach is look,
we know when the calendar is. The only reason we're keeping it
is because the Rabbi told us it's a תקנה. takana. If it's
a תקנה takana then it all it's all one big unit. Whereas
the other approach is saying no no no, it's not a תקנה.
takana. If it were a תקנה takana then you wouldn't have a
distinction that the areas near Israel have to keep do one day
and the areas far away do two. When did you ever hear
about a rabbinic תקנה takana that made like those types of lines
and distinctions? Or let's assume that we were you know that we
got came back to a period where they could get the information
out in a faster way, then presumably the areas that would be
able then presumably we would stop doing it. Well if it was
a rabbinic תקנה takana we wouldn't stop doing it. So the fact
is he's what אביי Abaye saying is we're clearly just reflecting the
reality of the practice that was at that time. And that's why
you can distinguish between places near Israel, places away from Israel, why
in theory things would be different. If the times, if the circumstances
were different, it's all just to reflect the reality of that practice.
And therefore, if it's keeping up the מנהג, minhag, well the nature
of that is I don't know which day is יום טוב. Yom
Tov Is it the first? Is it the second? So since the
reality of when it was practiced that way is not being certain
which day was יום טוב Yom Tov, and which day wasn't, that's
the idea of שתי קדושות—each shtei kedushos day is independent. Is that
clear? Yes? No? Sort of? If it's a תקנה, takanah, then the
rabbis told us to do it, so just do it, just keep
two days יום טוב. Yom Tov, We call it a two-day יום
טוב. Yom Tov, So that makes it one unit. If it's continuing
the practice, then when they were practicing it, each day was independent.
One day was יום טוב, Yom Tov one wasn't. They didn't know
which was which. If our practice is a continuation of that, we
keep up that reality of it being a ספק. safek. And אביי
Abaye is indicating that that's true because of its
flexibility—this nature of who keeps it and under what circumstances reflects the
reality that it's a מנהג minhag and not a תקנה. takanah. I
want to say something about this point which maybe will help bring
it home, which is very, very relevant for contemporary issues. What happens
when somebody who lives in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz goes visit ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael for יום טוב? Yom Tov. Right? Do you keep
one day or two days? So when I was growing up, everybody
said, "Oh no, you absolutely have to keep two days." Only crazy
Zionist rabbis say you have to keep one day, but everybody else
says two days. Now the pendulum has swung, and many, many people
are doing one day. And what's that based on? So it's a
תשובה tshuva of the חכם צבי. Chacham Tzvi. And the חכם צבי
Chacham Tzvi says a very simple issue. He says,
"If you approach it like, okay, your מנהג minhag in חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz is two days, your practice is two days, so even
when you go to a place with a different practice, you keep
the practice of the place you came from." That's the logic of
keeping two days. But the חכם צבי Chacham Tzvi says, "No, no,
no, that's not the way to think about it. The way to
think about it is like this: Let's assume this was happening at
the time of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay? And you lived
in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz where there were two days you kept,
and you happened to be visiting ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for יום
טוב. Yom Tov. How many days would you keep? If it happened
at the time when they were doing it based on the witnesses,
you'd keep one day, because you would know when ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh was. So our whole practice of two days means to continue
how it would have been done at the time of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So at the time of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, if I was living in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz. and visited
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for יום טוב, Yom Tov I would have
kept one day. So that's what I'm going to do now." So
you see, so that is a nice way of showing what אביי
Abaye is trying to demonstrate. It's not like a flat תקנה—two takanah
days, that's the הלכה halacha for חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz, It's: "No,
I will practice how it would have been done in the time
of the בית המקדש." Beis Hamikdash. So no matter, am I far
away from Israel, am I close to Israel, according to the חכם
צבי, Chacham Tzvi, am I actually visiting Israel for יום טוב? Yom
Tov All those things you ask yourself, what would you have done
at the time of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Not, "Oh, you're
a בן חוץ לארץ, ben Chutz La'aretz, so your הלכה halacha is
two days." So that's exactly the debate that's going on. If it's
a תקנה, takanah, it's a קדושה אחת. kedusha achat, If it's a
מנהג, minhag, says אביי, Abaye, it's שתי קדושות. shtei kedushos. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara. continues. Okay,
השתא דידעינן בקביעא דירחא—now Hashta deyadeinan bekvia deyarcha here's the question: given
that we know of when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, is, מאי טעמא
עבדינן תרי יומי—why mai ta'ama avdinan terei yomei do we do two
days? According to אביי, Abaye, if it's not a תקנה, takanah, if
it's more this flexible reality of where you would—what you would have
done had you been around in the time of the בית המקדש?
Beis Hamikdash? So says משום
דשלחו מתם—they mishum deshalchu mitem sent from there from ארץ ישראל: Eretz
Yisrael: הזהרו במנהג אבותיכם בידיכם—be hizaharu beminhag avoteichem beyadeichem careful about the
practice of your forefathers in your hands, meaning keep the מנהגין. minhagin.
Now, that seems to be the whole message: those four words. But
now the גמרא Gemara elaborates, because maybe "keep the מנהגין" minhagin would
not have been enough to say why we give it all of
the weight that we give in reality and we absolutely פוסקים pasken
it as a reality of two days יום טוב. Yom Tov So
the גמרא Gemara now adds the following line: זימנין דגזרה המלכות
גזירה—there zimnin degazra hamalchut gezeira will be a time
when the government will make an edict
ואתי לאקלקולי—and ve-atei leakalkulei it'll come to be מקלקל, mekalkel, which means
that even if we know when the calendar is—I just want to
sort of read where, hold on, just רש"י. Rashi Right,
רש"י Rashi says that even though we know when the calendar is,
there might be a time when because when we're under a persecution
when we'll lose access
to that knowledge, to that store, to the traditions of the calendar
and how to fix the calendar, and then we really won't know
which day is יום טוב. Yom Tov So since it's possible there'll
come a time where we really won't know, make sure to keep
this practice of two days. So again, that's like the בבלי—you Bavli
can tell from the shift from Hebrew to Aramaic—that's the בבלי's Bavli
way of reinforcing this. Because if it's just a מנהג, minhag, there
are a lot of things that are מנהגים minhagim that we don't
treat with that absolute weight of two days of יום טוב. Yom
Tov So saying: "No, no, no, it's not just סתם stam a
מנהג, minhag, it's a מנהג minhag that you have to be very
deeply worried about right now because there might become a future reality
where there is a real ספק." safek. But again, notice that it's
rooted in this issue of ספק—of safek a you won't know. And
that's what אביי Abaye is—and that's what אביי Abaye is saying here:
that we go like רב that it's שתי קדושות shtei kedushos because
it's rooted in a reality of ספק, safek, and each one is
independent. So that was an interesting debate about a normal שני ימים
טובים. Now we're going to get to two days of ראש השנה?
Rosh Hashanah? So שני ימים טובים של ראש השנה, shenei yamim tovim
shel Rosh Hashanah, what's the story about two days of ראש השנה?
Rosh Hashanah רבה ושמואל בר אמי תרווייהו, Rabba u'Shmuel bar Ammi tarvayhu,
so רבה Rabba and שמואל Shmuel both say, מודו בזה אסור בזה,
modu bazei asuru bazei,
that's different. There, even the same רב that said a normal two
days יום טוב is each day is independent, two days of ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah. is one continuous קדושה. Kedusha, And if it's born
on one, it's forbidden on the other, just like it's born in
the middle of the day, because it's all one big continuous two-day
קדושה. kedusha? דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה. Mishnah. בראשונה, barishona,
originally, היו מקבלין עדות החודש כל היום. hayu mekabelin edut hachodesh kol
hayom.
They would accept testimony of when the new month was the whole
day of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is very
tricky, right? Which day you celebrate as ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah when
you actually didn't have a fixed calendar could only be determined in
the middle of the day, because the witnesses would have seen the
new moon the night before and they would come the following day
and that would be the middle of day one, so the initial
practice of day one of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. was always in
doubt until the witnesses came because maybe the witnesses won't come today
and then tomorrow will be the first day of ראש חודש תשרי,
Rosh Chodesh Tishrei, tomorrow will be ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah, So the
first day was always in doubt based on whether the witnesses would
show up today or not.
פעם אחת, pa'am achat, so they would be willing to accept the
witnesses, they would be willing, maybe you could scoot over there and
I'm sorry I don't know, some people clearly they cleared out the
גמרא Gemara says. Okay,
where were we? Okay, בראשונה היו מקבלין עדות החודש כל היום, barishona
hayu mekabelin edut hachodesh kol hayom, they would originally accept testimony of
which day was ראש חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh Tishrei the entire day
one, the day after the twenty-ninth of אלול. Elul. פעם אחת, pa'am
achat, one time, נשתהו עדים לבוא. nishtahu edim lavo. The witnesses came
late. They came towards the very end of the day. And what
were they doing? So there were no witnesses yet, so they assumed,
okay, no witnesses are coming, today isn't going to be ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh. tomorrow will be ראש חודש and they brought the קרבן
מנחה Korban Mincha and what happened? ונתקלקלו הלוים בשיר. vnitkalkalu haLevi'im bashir.
And the לוים Levi'im messed up, they sang the wrong song. Because
what happens is
on a יום טוב the מוסף Musaf would have a separate שיר
של יום shir shel yom unique to יום טוב and the תמיד
tamid of the afternoon would also have, not the same as מוסף,
Musaf, but a separate שיר של יום shir shel yom because it
was יום טוב. You would have a different שיר, shir, we learned
earlier about the idea of the time the wine was poured at
the communal sacrifice and the לוים Levi'im sang a שיר, shir, so
that would be at the תמיד, tamid, it would be at the
מוסף, Musaf, and the שיר shir would either be, there would be
a standard one during the weekday, we say that at the end
of דאווענינג davening and then a special one for יום טוב, the
special one for the מוסף Musaf of יום טוב and a related
special one for the תמידים tamidim of יום טוב. Now שחרית Shacharit
you never knew, right? שחרית Shacharit you always as רש"י Rashi says,
every single ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah שחרית תמיד Shacharit tamid was way
too early to know whether it was going to be ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah or not. So there it was established that you just
do the regular weekday one. If it was a Wednesday you did
the Wednesday one. Could it be a Wednesday? It can't be a
Wednesday. If it was a Tuesday, according to our calendar, then it
could have been. Anyway, you would do the regular weekday one. But
by מוסף Musaf and מנחה, Mincha, then you would know whether it
was ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah or not and you'd do the right
one. But what happened is they assumed nobody had come yet, they
assumed in the end it was a weekday, so came the מנחה
Mincha and they did the weekday one again and that was a
mess up because by the מנחה, Mincha, the תמיד, tamid, I shouldn't
say the תמיד שבין הערבים, tamid shebein ha'arbayim, forget מנחה, Mincha, whatever,
the תמיד שבין הערבים, tamid shebein ha'arbayim, the afternoon תמיד tamid is
the one that's supposed to have the one unique to the day
or specific to the day. Now תוספות Tosafot asks the obvious question
which is there's a bigger problem which is all of the מוסף
קרבנות. Musaf korbanot. Did they bring them or not bring them? Okay,
and if they didn't bring them yet, then can you really bring
them after the afternoon תמיד? tamid? So normally you're not supposed to
bring anything after the afternoon תמיד. tamid. So תוספות Tosafot says yeah,
בדיעבד bidi'avad in this circumstance they would have brought the מוסף Musaf
after the afternoon תמיד tamid and therefore part of the mess up
was not just that they sang the wrong שיר, shir, but part
of the mess up is that they would have to have brought
the מוסף, Musaf, right, because if they assumed it was going to
turn out to be a weekday, they weren't bringing the מוסף. Musaf.
They said okay, let's get on with the תמיד tamid and it's
a weekday and say the weekday שיר shir and then oh my
God, they found out it was ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah now they're
going to have to bring the מוסף Musaf after the תמיד. tamid.
So and that's in the גמרא Gemara in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
which discusses it, that's sort of alluded to as well, that problem.
Okay, so this was a mess up. The witnesses came late and
it was a mess up, they sang the wrong שיר, shir, we're
going to have to bring the מוסף Musaf later, it was a
problem. So what are we going to do to make sure this
problem doesn't happen again? התקינו, hitkinu, they established שלא יהיו מקבלין את
העדים אלא עד המנחה shelo yehu mekabelin et ha'edim ela ad haMincha
that no, after מנחה Mincha time, meaning after the time that you
bring, which מנחה Mincha time is linked to the afternoon תמיד, tamid,
after the מנחה Mincha time, after the afternoon תמיד tamid would be
brought, no more witnesses. So if witnesses have not come yet and
it's time for the תמיד, tamid, we're bringing the תמיד, tamid, it's
going to be a weekday, we're singing the weekday שיר, shir, and
if witnesses come And they want to make today ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*, we’re closing the door on them. All right. Now
בנוגע *b'noge-a*... ואם באו מן המנחה למעלה *v'im bo-u min ha-minchah l'malah*,
now the עדים eidim *eydim* did show up. What do you do?
So we’re slamming the door in their face. We know tomorrow is
going to be ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*. Okay. Once it’s
מנחה Mincha *minchah* time, we’re not listening to them. So, nevertheless, נוהגין
אותו היום קדש ולמחר קדש *nogin oso hayom kodesh u'l'machar kodesh*. This
is what’s the relevant point. Even though you won’t accept the witnesses
anymore and that allows you to go ahead and say the weekday
שיר של יום *Shir Shel Yom* and not to bring the מוסף
*Mussaf*. Nevertheless, from this period of מנחה Mincha *minchah* time to the
end of the day of day one, you know once it becomes
מנחה Mincha? *minchah* time, what do you know? You know that even
if witnesses come, you won’t accept them. So once it becomes מנחה
Mincha *minchah* time, you know that today is not going to be
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*, right? That’s because you know, even
if witnesses show up, too late. Nevertheless, so as not to undermine
the seriousness of keeping the beginning of the day ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*, we’re going to continue keeping the day with the
sanctity of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*. We’re going to continue
not doing מלאכה *melachah* till the end of the day. And you
understand why that is, because if in the middle of a day
you would say, 'Okay everybody, you can start doing מלאכה *melachah*,' then
next year, I’m going to start doing מלאכה *melachah* at the beginning
of the day. So in order to keep the weight of the
day serious, because you don’t know how it’ll play out, you’re going
to keep the whole day even once it becomes מנחה Mincha *minchah*
time. Now what does that mean? That means that there were circumstances
when you would keep two days of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh
Hashanah*, even though you knew that only the second day was going
to be the real ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*, right? Any
case where witnesses came after מנחה Mincha *minchah* would be a case
where you would keep two days ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*
even though it would only be the second one which would be
the real one. So that’s not even a question of ספק safek,
*safek*. I know tomorrow’s going to be ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, *Rosh
Hashanah*, but nevertheless, because I have to keep finishing out today as
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*. So therefore that establishes this idea
of קדושה kedusha, אחתא *kedusha achta*. Like we said before, if it’s
a מנהג *minhag* and it’s based on doubt, that’s שתי קדושות Shtei
Kedushot. *shetei kedushot*. If the Rabbis are telling you, 'Do it anyway.
Here’s what you gotta do. You gotta keep today and tomorrow's ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*,' even though you know what’s what, that
creates a reality of a two-day unit. Okay, so that’s the idea
that we have, it’s called יומא אריכתא *Yoma Arichta*. You might know
this. And that has a lot of relevance not just with cases
of עדים Edim *eydim*, most of us don’t have the עדים Edim
*eydim* question, but questions about שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu*, the whole idea of
like the new fruit and whatever to allow us to say a
שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* on the second night. Because normally you say a שהחיינו
*Shehecheyanu* on the second night of יום טוב *Yom Tov* because we
suspect maybe yesterday was חול *chol* and today is יום טוב *Yom
Tov*. But here, if it’s one big unit, it’s not based on
doubt, it’s based on you know, but nevertheless keep two days, then
it creates this reality of one extended קדושה kedusha. *kedusha*. And that’s
the position of רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*. Okay, so that’s רב ושמואל
*Rav u'Shmuel*'s idea that it’s קדושה kedusha, אחתא *kedusha achta* because of
that תקנה takkanah *takanah* which had it not based on doubt but
was a definite knowledge there would still be two days. אמר רבא
Rava *Amar Rava*, says רבא Rava *Rava*, מתקנת רבן יוחנן בן זכאי
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai ואילך *mitakanas Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai va'eilach*, from
the תקנה takkanah, *takanah* of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai *Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai* onwards after the בית המקדש Bais Hamikdash
*Beis HaMikdash* was destroyed, ביצה Beitzah מותרת *beitzah muteres*, things reversed themselves
and the egg now becomes permissible, meaning that it now is שתי
קדושות shei kedushos. *shetei kedushot* and not קדושה kedusha אחתא *kedusha achta*.
Why is it? דתנן *ditnan*, we taught in a משנה Mishna: *Mishnah*
in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*, משחרב בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
*mishecharav Beis HaMikdash*, from when the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*
was destroyed, התקין רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai *hiskin
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai* שמקבלין עדות eidus החדש כל היום *she'mekablin eidus
hachodesh kol hayom*. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai *Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai* said, 'Okay, no longer בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis
HaMikdash*, no reason to shut the door in the face of the
witnesses, no problem with the sacrifices, we can accept witnesses till the
very end of the day.' Okay, makes a lot of sense, right?
Why keep that old תקנה takkanah *takanah* in place? Let's accept witnesses
till the end of the day. If we’re now accepting witnesses till
the end of the day, right, we’re back to the point that
there’s no תקנה takkanah, *takanah* to keep today as ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah* even though I know otherwise. We go back to
the reality like any normal two-day יום טוב *Yom Tov*. If you’re
keeping two days, it’s because of doubt, it’s not because of a
תקנה takkanah, *takanah*, because now עדות *eidus* can come the whole day.
אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye, *Amar lei Abaye*, so אביי Abaye
*Abaye* said back to רבא Rava *Rava*, והא רב ושמואל דאמרי דתרוייהו
*duvayhu* ביצה אסורה *beitzah asurah*. Okay, I understand your stand, your idea
that רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai *Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai*, you know, switched things about the testimony, but how do you
assume that means that the הלכה halacha *halacha* of שתי קדושות shei
kedushos. *shetei kedushot* or קדושה kedusha. אחתא *kedusha achta* switches? רב ושמואל
*Rav u'Shmuel* both say that it still has the הלכה halacha? *halacha*
of קדושה kedusha, אחתא *kedusha achta*, that the egg is forbidden. אמר
ליה *Amar lei*, so רבא Rava. *Rava* said back, אמינא לך אנא
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai ואת אמרת לי רב
ושמואל *amina lach ana Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai v'at amrat li Rav
u'Shmuel*? I tell you רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai *Rabban
Yochanan ben Zakkai*, I show you a משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, the logic
dictates that now it’s שתי קדושות shei kedushos? *shetei kedushot* because it
would only be based on an issue of ספק safek. *safek*, not
on an issue of תקנה takkanah, *takanah*, and you’re saying, 'Oh, how
could I say that? What about רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*?' No! How
could רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel* say what they said based on what
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai *Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai* did?
Okay, I have רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Yochanan ben Zakkai *Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai* behind me. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, 'Okay, you
know what, that's a good point.' ולרב ושמואל קשיא מתניתין *u'l'Rav u'Shmuel
kashya masnisin*? So what do רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel* do with the
reality of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי *Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai*? How do
they still feel it's קדושה kedusha אחתא *kedusha achta*? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, לא קשיא lo kashya. *lo kashya*, that's not difficult.
הא לן והא להו *ha lan ha lehu*. That's for them, this
is for us. Okay, what does that mean? So what it means
is is that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* it goes
back to being שתי קדושות shei kedushos? *shetei kedushot*. Why? Because in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*... Reality of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי.
How do they still feel it's one קדושה? kedusha. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא lo, קשיא. That's not difficult. הא לן הא להו.
ha lan ha lehu. That's for them, this is for us. Okay?
What does that mean? So what it means is that in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael, it goes back to being two קדושות. kedushot. Why?
Because in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, there could have been a reality
after that after the רבן יוחנן בן זכאי's תקנה takkanah there could
have been a reality of one day ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, when
the witnesses would have come on. Well, there could have been a
reality after that, that after, you know, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי's תקנה,
takkanah there could have been a reality of one day ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah Witnesses would have come on the first day, early in
the day or even late in the day, and it would have
been a one day ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah So therefore,
they had gone in Israel they would go from two days, which
they would sometimes keep two days, you know, based on this sort
of תקנה takkanah of keep it because once it's after מנחה Mincha
time you keep, you know, you keep two days, you're always going
to keep two days. They once רבן יוחנן בן זכאי said we
can accept witnesses from מנחה onwards, and so now sometimes it'll be
one day, sometimes it'll be two days, even when the witnesses come
late it'll be one day. So therefore, even when we're going to
go back to keeping now if there will be a יום טוב
which we'll keep, a year which we'll keep two days in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael it won't be based on the תקנה, takkanah, old
תקנה, takkanah it'll be based on just we don't know, right? The
witnesses, you know, the witnesses we didn't hear whether the witnesses came
or not, it'll be based on issues of doubt. Okay? Or it'll
be a reality that the witnesses didn't come and we wound up
keeping the whole first day, but we kept the whole first day
not because of תקנה, takkanah. we kept the whole first day because
at any minute the witnesses might come, so we kept it out
of doubt. So that's why in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael it switches
to this issue of ספק, safek. because that reflected the reality, and
therefore the two days would be two days based on ספק. safek.
You're waiting the whole day, keeping it because maybe the witnesses will
come, that's an issue of ספק. safek According to however in חוץ
לארץ, Chutz La'aretz רש״י Rashi points out we never stopped keeping two
days. Right, in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz we would all even after
the תקנה takkanah shifted, there would never be a reality of keeping
one day, as we know in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz, every יום
טוב is a two day יום טוב, right? So since there would
always be the reality of two days in חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz
this is the way רש״י Rashi explains, even
since the two days began as an idea of קדושה אחת, kedusha
achat even when the reality changed in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that
now they could accept witnesses the whole day and the תקנה Takanah.
goes away, since we began observing the two days as קדושה אחת
kedusha achat and that practice always continued, there was never a break
in the practice, even though the existing logic has shifted, once we
kept that תקנה Takanah and we continued it, it always had the
way it was initially established, which was one קדושה. kedusha But in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael basically the reality not only the reality
shifted, the practice shifted. Once it started accepting witnesses the whole day,
they would sometimes keep only one day יום טוב, and therefore it
was always based on even when they kept two days it was
based on a reality of ספק. safek, I don't know if that's
so clear. תוספות סוכה Tosafot Sukkah has another explanation because it's not
so transparent or obvious, but the basic point is that in חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz we kept, I'll make it simple, in חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz we have an idea of a two day יום טוב,
and that idea of a two day יום טוב which we've always
practiced in the case of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. started off as
one קדושה kedusha. because of the early idea of not accepting witnesses
and that's the way it remains. In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, where
they have mostly one day יום טובס Yom Tovs and every now
and then they'll have a two day ראש השנה Rosh Hashana. because
they won't know whether the witnesses are coming, that shifts to a
reality of ספק safek. and not a reality of קדושה אחת Kedusha
Achat. but of ספק קדושה. safek kedusha. Yes.
למעשה, L'maise, the first day,
everyone in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz observes
that day from the morning on.
Yes, and starting from the evening before.
In ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael
if they found out if witnesses came, they got the message,
they would not have kept the second day.
Right. Yes, they would not have to keep the second day יום
טוב. But they kept that first day. But if they didn't come
on the but
they kept their first day, the thirtieth day after ראש חודש אלול.
Rosh Chodesh Elul. Right.
So if witnesses came on that day, then they would not keep
two days יום טוב.
But they start off keeping that day from the night
before, but they have to start keeping it because the witnesses might
show up today, and they have to keep the whole day through
because witnesses might show up till the very last minute.
And previous to this תקנה, Takanah, they would have kept it until
מנחה?
No, no, no. Previous to
this—no, no, no, it's the opposite. Previous to this reversal of the
תקנה Takanah of accepting the witnesses, they also would have kept the
whole two days, but the difference would be that they would have
kept the end of the first day even when they knew that
the official ראש השנה Rosh Hashana was really going to be tomorrow.
Right. Once it got to be מנחה time, right, they knew that
the official ראש השנה Rosh Hashana for calendarical purposes was tomorrow because
they couldn't accept witnesses anymore, and nevertheless they kept they kept it.
So when they were keeping the end of day one, they were
not keeping it because of ספק, Safeik. they were keeping it because
of the תקנה.
Takanah
But the morning of day one
they were keeping because of ספק. safek, But the end of day
one also?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The whole point is they started keeping it, right, but then they
could they didn't want them to—because you still have the reality today
might turn out to be ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. Okay? Is that
clear? Maybe that wasn't as clear as I needed to be before.
But basically, the way it used to be is
thirtieth day of אלול Elul rolls around. Today
witnesses might show up today, so you start keeping today as ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashanah If witnesses do show up today, it turns out
today was ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana so you start keeping the whole
day as ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana It used to be, once the
original תקנה Takanah. was in place, that would come מנחה time and
you would know, okay, I know tomorrow on the calendar is going
to be תשרי Tishrei one. But now nevertheless, you still would keep
the entire day, the end of the day, and you wouldn't start
doing מלאכה, because that would undermine what you had done earlier. So
that would be a reality where you would keep two days of
ראש השנה Rosh Hashana, when there was a period which wasn't in
doubt. The end of day one wasn't in doubt and you were
still keeping it. And because it wasn't based on doubt, that's the
idea of קדושה אחת. Kedusha Achat. Okay, but once they allowed the
witnesses to come the whole day, then it was then the only
reason to keep keeping to keep doing it the whole day was
because of the reality of doubt, not because of this תקנה. Takanah
I'm losing I'm still losing you, but okay. Alright, clear pretty much?
Questions? Okay. By the way, here's an important thing to realize about
this, which is that ראש השנה Rosh Hashana is the to show
you the difference between the whole sort of תקנה Takanah, versus doubt
issue. When we normally keep two days of ראש חודש, which day
is the actual day one of the month? Second day ראש חודש.
When we keep two days of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana which day
is day one of the month? First day. Right? Why is that?
Because that basically reflects the reality not when the witnesses would come
the second day, which is the reality of doubt, and you only
kept the first day because of ספק. safek That reflects the reality
when the witnesses would come on the first day, but they would
come too late, right? And if they came on the first day,
but they came too late, then the then, you know, okay, now,
you know, there they made the calendrical day day one. But nevertheless,
you know, the reality was was that day was always going to
be kept as ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana. you know, regardless, and therefore
and then the second day. So it reflects a different type of
a reality, and that's the issue. So basically what we are saying
is that when it used to be there was a period of
time when they didn't accept witnesses where they would keep two days
even though part of that would not based on doubt. And therefore
that has a reality of קדושה אחת. Kedusha Achat Now that they
reversed that תקנה, Takanah the only reason you keep two days is
because of the issue of doubt and makes it שתי קדושות. Shte
Kedushot. Okay. Nevertheless, in בחוץ לארץ B'chutz La'aretz it continues to reflect
the old reality because the practice continued consistently and therefore in חוץ
לארץ Chutz La'aretz the two days is one קדושה. kedusha. Now what
you might be asking yourself is, so how come in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael? A, do they believe in the idea of one קדושה
kedusha. of two days ראש השנה Rosh Hashana and B, why do
they even keep two days of ראש השנה Rosh Hashana in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael if the idea is that the reality switched in
ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael So we'll get to that. Let's keep on
going in the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, מאי טעמא? Mai Ta'ama?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: רב יוסף אמר, Rav
Yosef Amar, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, אף משתקנת רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי ואילך ביצה אסורה, Af Mishtakanat Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai V'eilach
Beitzah Asurah, yes, even after רבן יוחנן בן זכאי reversed the תקנה
Takanah. of accepting witnesses, the egg remains forbidden. Now why? So before
we said because, you know, that was a continuous practice in חוץ
לארץ chutz la'aretz and the and it didn't change. He has a
different idea. מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama, what's the reason? הוי דבר שבמנין
וכל דבר שבמנין צריך מנין אחר להתירו, Havei Davar Sheb'minyan V'chol Davar
Sheb'minyan Tzarich Minyan Acher L'hatirow,
because the egg being if born on day one being forbidden on
day two was a matter of
in number, but meaning something that was voted. Okay, it was an
official edict of the rabbis that was voted into law, and therefore
you need another act to retract it, which basically is the principle,
this tends to be sort of, you know, extended to all דרבננ'ס
D'rabanans or תקנות דרבנן, Takanot D'rabanan, that even when the circumstances change,
the תקנה takanah doesn't go away automatically. You need an active act
of legislation of the rabbis to re to retract the תקנה. takanah.
The תקנה takanah, doesn't fall by the wayside just because the reality
changed. So what he is saying is, it's true, now we can
accept witnesses. The reality has changed. But the way in which the
קדושה kedusha. was established as one קדושה, kedusha. that's not retracted. That
remains that way and it will not change unless it's officially been
retracted. So what was retracted was accepting the witnesses. What wasn't retracted
was the nature of the two days of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana
Okay, but let's see where we go with this. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. And now we're going to digress to
this very important discussion of קדושה אחת kedusha achas.
of צריך מנין אחר להתירו. Tzarich Minyan Acher L'hatirow. So
אמר רב יוסף מנא אמינא לה, Amar Rav Yosef Mana Amina Lah,
where do I get this idea that you need an official act
to retract something that was
established? דכתיב, Dich'tiv, the verse says. Now I want to just point
out before we start reading the verses, that what do you mean
where do you know this from? I mean it's like one of
the early משניות in עדיות Eduyot says, you know, that any בית
דין Beis Din that makes a you know תקנה, takana you can't
reverse it unless you have another בית דין Beis Din that's גדול
הימנו בחכמה ובמנין. Gadol Heimenno B'chochmah U'b'minyan. So of course, isn't that
the same saying the same thing? But what רב יוסף Rav Yosef
seems to be saying is making an even sharper point. He's saying
not only do you need a legislation to remove an old תקנה
takana סתם, Stam, even when the reasons, even when the circumstances have
changed, it doesn't fall by the wayside. You need an active תקנה.
takana, And that's like a really important question להלכה. L'halacha. If you
have a certain דרבנן D'rabanan that's based on certain reality, does does
it change when those circumstances change? For example, the גמרא Gemara says
don't drink milk unless you have a Jew supervising it because maybe
טרפה Treifah milk was mixed in. Well, let's say you have circumstances
in which you know טרפה Treifah milk wasn't mixed it was no
concern it might have been mixed in. the reality of dairy farms
in the United States. So does that תקנה takana. automatically go away?
Okay, and that's the whole issue about חלב עכו"ם cholov akkum and
חלב סתם cholov stam and all those questions. Okay, so that's what
he says. Yes, the reality has changed. They now accept witnesses. Doesn't
mean the הלכה halacha has changed. Okay, you would need a specific
act of legislation to retract the earlier תקנה. takana Now he's going
to demonstrate that. So let's take a look. מנא הני מילי? Mina
hani mili? דכתיב, Dechtiv, the verse says: לכו אמרו להם שובו לכם
לאהליכם. Lechu imru lahem shuvu lachem l'ohaleichem. Okay, at the end of
מעמד הר סיני, Ma'amad Har Sinai, God says to משה, Moshe, go
tell them go back to their tents, which means to be with
their wives. ואומר, V'omer,
and the verse says: במשך היובל המה יעלו בהר. Bimshoch hayovel heyma
ya'alu bahar.
When the ram's horn is blown is extended, you know, it's blown
a long blast, they can go up to the mountain, because they
also weren't allowed on the mountain during that period. And ותנן, U'tenan,
and we saw in the משנה: כרם רבעי היה עולה לירושלים מהלך
יום אחד לכל צד. Kerem revai haya oleh l'Yerushalayim mahalakh yom echad
l'chol tzad. Now again, it's not clear what these things are proving.
We're going to read them and then the גמרא's Gemara going to
unpack them. So כרם רבעי היה עולה לירושלים מהלך יום אחד לכל
צד. Kerem revai haya oleh l'Yerushalayim mahalakh yom echad l'chol tzad.
Now if you have כרם רבעי, kerem revai, fourth year of your
of your of your vine being planted, the grapes from the fourth
year, what's the הלכה? halacha. You bring it up to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and you eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Now that would be a
schlepp, so what a lot of people would prefer to do is
to transfer that to money and just bring the money up to
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not actually transfer the fruit. The other good thing about
that is, if you have to bring the fruit then you have
to do it within a certain period of time before the fruit
goes bad. To transfer to money, you can just like store it
all up and wait till you're going to be עולה לרגל oleh
l'regel or something. But the רבנן Rabbanan said that if you live
within one day's journey of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, we're not going to let
you transfer to money. We're going to insist that you bring the
fruit up. Why? So it'll be the experience that the תורה Torah
imagines, everybody bringing their fruit into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and that'll be a
very beautiful experience for everybody. We're going to make that demand if
you actually are within one day's journey. Okay, so היה עולה לירושלים,
haya oleh l'Yerushalayim, you would have to bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim
and not redeem it. מהלך יום אחד לכל צד, mahalakh yom echad
l'chol tzad, one day's—if you're within one day's journey of ירושלים Yerushalayim
in any direction. וזו היא תחומה, V'zo hi techuma, this is the
boundaries of that one day journey. אילת מן
הדרום. Eilat min hadarom. That's obviously—see, there's questions here about the about
the text and about which places they're referring to, but we'll read
it with the sort of marginal corrections. So it says אילת Eilat
is in the south. Is אילת Eilat only one day's journey from
ירושלים Yerushalayim in those days? I don't know. I don't know how
long one day's journey would be. Twenty miles or something? What? Well,
if that's your גרסא, girsa, presumably how how south is אילת Eilat
from ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Anybody know? Five hours by car, yeah. It cannot
be that אילת. Eilat. So anyway, maybe it's עקרבת מן הצפון Akrabat
min hatzafon as opposed to אילת מן הדרום. Eilat min hadarom. Okay,
ועקרבת מן הצפון v'Akrabat min hatzafon
according to this version צפון, tzafon, עקרבת Akrabat in the north. I
don't know where עקרבת Akrabat is identified now, maybe it's עקרבת Akrabat
in the south. Anyway, the last two are clearer. לוד מן המערב,
Lod min hama'arav, לוד Lod in the west, הירדן מן המזרח hayarden
min hamizrach and the Jordan in the east. Right? The Jordan is
the east of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. לוד, Lod, לוד, Lod, I should have
said it, excuse me, לוד Lod is in the west of ירושלים—west
Yerushalayim of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So ואמר
עולא, v'amar Ulla, how far is לוד Lod from ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Right?
Take the drive to the airport, half hour, right? So yeah, I
don't think we could be comparing לוד Lod to אילת. Eilat. So
alright, fine.
And it only takes about a half hour to get to the
Jordan? Probably if you if you would go straight, yeah, if you'd
go straight straight east. Okay. Alright. ותנן. U'tenan. Okay. ואמר עולא. v'amar
Ulla. Now עולא Ulla said, ותימא רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן. v'teima Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan. מה טעם? Ma
ta'am?
What's the reason behind this? כדי לעטר שוקי ירושלים בפירות. Kedei le'ater
shukei Yerushalayim b'peirot. In order
that the that the marketplaces of ירושלים Yerushalayim should be adorned with
fruit. Everybody should be bringing all of their fruit, you know, it'll
be a very beautiful experience. Okay. Now the that purpose of the
reason is critical, because part of what he's proving again is not
just that you need legislation to retract the תקנה, takana, but you
need it even when the reasons, even when the circumstances have changed,
behind the reasons have changed. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא:
braita: כרם רבעי היה לו לרבי אליעזר במזרח לוד. Kerem revai haya
lo l'Rabbi Eliezer bemizrach Lod. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
had כרם רבעי kerem revai in the east of לוד. Lod. Now
east of לוד, Lod, it was within a day of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
right? Because because לוד Lod is to the west, so was east
of לוד, Lod, so was within a day of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. בצד
כפר טבי, Besad Kfar Tebi,
by the side of the village of טבי. Tebi. וביקש להפקירו לעניים.
U'vikeish le'afkiro l'aniyim. He didn't want to schlepp it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
okay? So he said, you know what, I'll just הפקיר hefker to
the poor. Let the poor get it, free food for them, they'll
take it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they'll eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and
I won't have to schlepp there. Better for me to give it
to the poor and not to have to schlepp. Let them take
it, it'll be a nice bonus for them, they'll go to ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, they'll eat it there. אמרו לו תלמידיו, Amru lo talmidav, his
students said to him: רבי, נמנו עליך חבריך והתירו. Rebbi, nimnu alecha
chaveirecha v'hitiru. Your
your colleagues have already voted and retracted it, okay? Meaning that this
was after חורבן הבית. churban habayit. So after the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash is destroyed and you basically do not have a active Jewish
population in Jerusalem, there is no longer the need to insist that
everybody bring their fruit up to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, okay, it's basically no
longer like this beautiful you know vibrant Jewish city that you want
to insist that all of that all the fruit is brought there.
So they already retracted it. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara explains
what's the proof about this? The proof is the following. טעמא Ta'ama
the reason he didn't have to worry about it was דנמנו. denimnu.
It says they took a new vote and they retracted it. הלאו
נמנו לא, halo nimnu lo, if they didn't take a vote, it
would not have fallen off by itself. The תקנה takana would have
remained even though the circumstances have changed. So that's clear what that
proof is. The proof from that story. They had to have a
vote to retract it. What about the proof from the biblical verses?
What were we trying to do with that? מאי באומר? Mai ba'omer?
What were you trying to do with the biblical verses? So הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is how this is the proof from the
verses. מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look. כתיב Kesiv היו נכונים לשלושת
ימים אל תגשו אל אשה. heyu nechonim lishloshes yamim al tigshu el
isha. It says be ready for three days, do not have any
contact with women, which basically again
is
raises other problems that if you read the פסוקים pesukim it really
sounds like God is talking about giving the תורה Torah to the
men. Don't have any contact with women so He's talking to the
men. And then the way but it's quite fascinating I just need
to make this point that sort of reads Judith Plaskow's this famous
Jewish feminist write a book Standing Again at Sinai. So the first
time where were the women? God seems that God was talking only
to the men. But the חזל Chazal quite
interestingly go out of their way to point out that the women
were there. Like the famous חזל Chazal of כה תאמר לבית יעקב
ותגיד לבני ישראל. koh somar l'veis Yaakov v'sageid livnei Yisrael. בית יעקב
אלו הנשים. Bais Yaakov eilu hanashim. בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael atah amarta
l'vnei the school בית יעקב Bais Yaakov gets its name from that
דרשה. drasha. So very much sort of sees that women are makes
a point that women are there. And they explain the reason of
the three days is not because you men can't have sex within
three days. It actually explains it's in order to enable the women
to be at הר סיני Har Sinai because if they've had recently
had sex with their husband and semen might still come out of
their body that would make them impure. So they explain the whole
reason for this idea was not to allow the men to be
at הר סיני Har Sinai but allow the women. Okay just needed
to say that. Now moving on the point being that they were
told not to have sex for three days prior to מעמד הר
סיני. ma'amad Har Sinai. Now
אל תגשו אל אשה. al tigshu el isha. So לכו אמרו להם
שובו לכם לאהליכם, lechu imru lahem shuvu lachem l'aholeichem, so then why
did God have to say go back to your tents? למה לי?
Lama li? Why was that needed? Why was that needed?
Obviously after it was done and you got your תורה Torah obviously
you could resume sex. So שמע מינה כל דבר שבמנין צריך מנין
אחר להתירו. shema mina kol davar she'biminyan tzarich minyan acher l'hatiro. Anything
that was once in a מנין, minyan, it's a funny phrase מנין,
minyan, but anything legislated let's put it that way needs another legislation
to retract it even though the reason has changed. Okay so they
were told not to have sex because of מעמד הר סיני ma'amad
Har Sinai so once מעמד הר סיני ma'amad Har Sinai was done
we should be able to have sex again but no you needed
an active act of legislation. Okay now and רב יוסף. Rav Yosef.
Yeah
so you have to change the word מנין minyan to mean legislation
not like
vote. Yes what would רב יוסף Rav Yosef have said about this?
I'm sure she would not have let me get through this גמרא
Gemara without being
interrupted. Yes it's really true.
Anyway so thank you for mentioning that. Now I want to make
a point here though about this idea because תוספות Tosafos is bothered.
If you take a look תוספות Tosafos I just need to show
you this one line of תוספות Tosafos on עמוד א amud aleph
look back at תוספות Tosafos כל דבר שבמנין צריך מנין אחר להתירו
kol davar she'biminyan tzarich minyan acher l'hatiro here's what תוספות Tosafos says.
יש היו רוצים לומר מכאן דאותן חרמות שעושים לזמן עד פסח או
עד זמן אחר וכי יגיע הזמן צריך מניין להתיר את החרם. yesh
hayortzim lomar mikan de'osan charamos she'osim lizman ad Pesach o ad zman
acher vechi yagia hazman tzarich minyan lehatir es hacherem. Meaning which is
this first a fascinating point which reflects a reality of the Middle
Ages and of the period of רשי Rashi and תוספות Tosafos and
so on where the way they would sort of back up תקנת
הקהל takanas hakahal is by making a חרם cherem right? Like we
know חרם רבינו גרשום. cherem Rabbeinu Gershom. And anybody who violates this
תקנה takana is under the ban is in under חרם. cherem. Now
let's say they said a certain thing would be for thirty days
there's a חרם cherem you can't do X or for the period
until פסח Pesach you're the חרם cherem I don't know everybody has
to give מעות חטין maos chitin or something. Okay now when פסח
Pesach comes you need to officially retract it? You said until פסח
Pesach so you would think it stops by itself but some people
would argue well how is this different? God said three days and
the גמרא Gemara says God needed to retract it right? So it
sounds like even if you build in a time limit you need
to officially retract it you understand the argument because of the similarity
to the idea of God saying three days. And תוספות Tosafos answers
no. God didn't say don't have sex for three days. Then you
wouldn't need to retract it then He's put in a time limit
in the In the תקנה takana *Takkanah*, you know, in the edict.
What God said was, be ready because three days from now there'll
be מעמד הר סיני *Ma'amad Har Sinai*, stop having sex. He didn't
ever say you don't have sex for three days. He said stop
having sex. Now you can infer that the reason to stop having
sex was because of מעמד הר סיני *Ma'amad Har Sinai*, and you
can infer that it should be logically allowable after מעמד הר סיני
*Ma'amad Har Sinai*, but none of that was said explicitly, right? All
it said is stop having sex now. So therefore you need another
act of legislation. But when it is built into the תקנה takana
*Takkanah*, then, right, then it's automatically the תקנה takana, *Takkanah* has an
expiration date and then you don't have to worry about it. Now
this by the way is very important because it goes back let's
say to that issue I raised you about about חלב ישראל *Cholov
Yisroel*. What's the logic to say that if you don't have a
concern of טרייף *treif* milk, that you don't have to worry about
you don't have to worry about, you know, about the תקנה takana.
*Takkanah* of needing a Jew to supervise. Right? It was established במנין
*be-minyan*, it was a תקנה takana. *Takkanah* that we needed a Jew
to supervise, who cares if the circumstances have changed. So then the
question always becomes by דרבננ'ס *d'rabbanan's*, how much were the circumstances built
into the תקנה takana *Takkanah*. Meaning how much was the תקנה Takana
*Takkanah* just flat, whatever our reasons are we're saying milk without Jewish
supervision is טרייף *treif*, okay? That even if whatever circumstances have changed,
that law is still on the books. Or no, maybe what we
said was, when there's a concern that there might be טרייף *treif*
milk mixed up, then it's without Jewish supervision it's טרייף *treif*. So
if you build in those factors into the תקנה Takana *Takkanah*, then
it will self-expire when those circumstances change. Okay, and that's exactly the
question that we ask by many דרבננ'ס *d'rabbanan's*, are the circumstances built
into the תקנה Takana *Takkanah* or not? So that's what תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafos* is saying. Here you needed it to be retracted because although
logically you could resume sex, that was never said explicitly. All it
said was stop having sex now. But if you build the circumstances
in and you say no, this is a three-day תקנה Takana *Takkanah*,
then it would go off by itself. Okay, so now that's the
proof from there. Now שמע מינה כל דבר שבמנין צריך מנין אחר
להתירו *Shema mina: kol davar she-be-minyan tzarich minyan acher l'hatiro*. So you
see that it needed to be actively retracted. Now וכי תימא *v'chi
teima*, now let's say you say I don't buy that proof. Why
not? Seems like a pretty good proof. למצות עונה הוא דאתא *L'mitzat
onah hu d'ata*. Maybe when it says go back to your tents,
it's not to make it allowed to have sex, it's to obligate
to have sex. You've been separate for three days, you have a
חיוב *chiyuv*, an obligation to go back and to resume sexual relations.
So therefore maybe it's not to retract the תקנה *Takkanah*, maybe it's
to create a חיוב *chiyuv*, an obligation. So let's try again. תא
שמע Tashma, *Ta shema*, let's try from this other story about מעמד
הר סיני *Ma'amad Har Sinai*. במשוך היובל המה יעלו בהר *Bimshoch hayovel
heimah ya'alu vahar*. When the horn trumpet sounds, then you can go
up to the mountain. מכדי *Michdi*, let's take a look, why did
you need to do that? Why did you need to say that?
כתיב גם הצאן והבקר אל ירעו אל מול ההר ההוא *Ksiv: "gam
hatzon vehabakar al yiru el mul hahar hahu"*, that the sheep and
cattle can't graze by that mountain. So obviously you know, and presumably
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* quotes a מדרש *Midrash*, "אל מול ההר ההוא" *el
mul hahar hahu*, that mountain means the mountain in which God's presence
is there. So you can logically understand that that problem would go
away automatically when God's presence had departed. So why did you need
במשוך היובל למה לי *bimshoch hayovel lama li*? Why did you need
the idea of sounding of the trumpet now it's permissible? I could
have figured that out myself, the whole problem was God's presence was
there. Obviously when that stopped, it stopped. No. שמע מינה כל דבר
שבמנין צריך מנין אחר להתירו *Shema mina: kol davar she-be-minyan tzarich minyan
acher l'hatiro*. It's very nice the circumstances have changed and logically it
shouldn't apply, but if that has not been built into the תקנה
*Takkanah*, you cannot retract it. You need an active act of legislation,
or here divine decree to retract. Okay, so this by the way
is a very important סוגיא sugya *sugya*, as you could imagine, an
extremely important סוגיא *sugya*, right? Because it says if it's broadened, what
is considered דבר שבמנין *davar she-be-minyan*? Is anything that's a דרבנן *d'rabbanan*
דבר שבמנין *davar she-be-minyan*? In הלכה *halacha* we tend to assume so,
and then it means that every דרבנן *d'rabbanan*, even when circumstances change,
the תקנה *Takkanah* remains in place. But then the question always becomes
as I've been saying to you, when are the circumstances built into
the תקנה *Takkanah*? How much does the תקנה *Takkanah* say when these
circumstances are present it's forbidden, or how much does the תקנה *Takkanah*
say it's just the flat rule? But if it's a flat rule,
then even when the circumstances change, it does not get retracted. Now
the מאירי *Meiri* discusses some exceptions where the change of circumstances might
be so drastic and that you would not need מנין אחר להתירו
*minyan acher l'hatiro*, and he has a whole hierarchy of how much
reason do you need and when you need a legislation and how
you need, you know, does it need to be a bigger בית
דין Beis Din *Beis Din*, not a bigger בית דין Beis Din
*Beis Din*? Basically saying if the reason has gone away, then even
a smaller בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din* can retract it. If
the reason hasn't gone away, then you need a bigger בית דין
Beis Din *Beis Din* to retract. So there's like a lot of
interesting complicated rules about the interrelationship between are the circumstances still present
and whether it needs active legislation to retract. But that is this
גמרא'ס *Gemara's* at least saying it with saying this point that Just
because the circumstances have changed does not mean it goes away. You
need, you need a new legislation. Now, getting back to our story
about the egg and ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana. so that's a whole
סוגיא by itself, but now let's get back to where we were
talking about, the egg and ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana? So he says,
"What are you telling me? יוחנן בן זכאי changed something and said
you can now accept witnesses, so the circumstances have changed, so now
it's no longer based on, now it's no longer based on תקנה,
now it's ספק, safek. and therefore should be two days and two
קדושות kedushot, and not one קדושה?" kedusha I'm sorry, even though the
circumstances change, that reality remains in place. It remains a reality of
one קדושה, kedusha not two קדושות. kedushot. That is his argument. So
let's take a look. Oh, I'm sorry, we have to finish the
proof. וכי תימא הני מילי דאורייתא, Vechi teima hani milei de'oraisa, you'll
say that is true maybe by biblical law, you know, by something
that God commands, אבל דרבנן, avel derabbanan, by rabbinic law, לא, maybe
you don't need another act of legislation. תא שמע, כרם רבעי, Kerem
Revai, the story of the case of the כרם רבעי. Kerem Revai.
דכרם רבעי דרבנן, Dekerem Revai derabbanan, that was rabbinic. דקאמרי ליה כבר
נמנו עליך חבריך והתירוה, Dekamrei lei kvar nimnu alecha chaveirecha vehitiruha,
you needed the fact that there was a new vote to retract
that תקנה. It did not fall aside by itself. Okay. וכי תימא
ביצה נמי נמנו עלה, Vechi teima beitzy nammi nimnu alei, יוחנן בן
זכאי ושריוה. vesharyuha. Now you'll say, okay,
so maybe the same way יוחנן בן זכאי retracted the תקנה about
the witnesses, maybe he retracted the issues around the egg and around
the two קדושות. kedushot? גמרא Gemara says, no. כי נמנו אעדות, Ki
imnu a'eidus, when they retracted they only retracted the issue about accepting
witnesses. אביצה לא נמנו, A'beitza lo imnu, but they never said the
issues for example about the egg, for born on the first day
forbidden on the second, that that they did not change. So the
reality of, again, when it was this issue of not accepting witnesses,
two days ראש השנה Rosh Hashana. were kept at times not because
of doubt but because of תקנה, and therefore it was a one
קדושה. kedusha, So what רב יוסף Rav Yosef is saying here is
even when that reality has shifted, the witness reality has shifted, the
halachic establishment of that as one קדושה, kedusha. that does not change
automatically. It would need a new act of legislation to change that
status. Okay, so that's his argument. Things remain the way they were.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara. says like this. One minute.
אמר ליה אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye said back to him. אטו, Atu,
one minute, says אביי, Abaye, ביצה במנין מי הוי? beitzy beminyan mi
havay? Whoever, when was there ever a תקנה about the egg? Nobody
ever got around and said, "Oh, let's legislate about an egg born
on day one that it should remain forbidden on day two," right?
That was never an act of legislation that needs to be reversed.
So ביצה בעדות תליא מילתא, beitzy be'eidus talya milsa, the issue about
the egg, which is really a stand-in for the idea of one
קדושה kedusha. or two קדושות, kedushos, was a, was a derivative, was
dependent on an outgrowth of the question of whether, of the reality
of the witnesses, whether they could be accepted or not. איסור עדות,
Issur eidus, when the witnesses were, were not accepted, when that תקנה
was in place, so that create, איסורא דביצה, itsa beitzy, the egg
born on day one is forbidden on day two. The non-accepting of
witnesses created the reality of one קדושה. kedusha. Okay? It, but it's
not like there was a תקנה of one קדושה, kedusha it was
a reality that was created as an outgrowth of not accepting the
witnesses. אישתרי עדות, Istari eidus, once witnesses were permitted, were accepted, then
אישתרי ביצה, istari beitzy, the egg becomes permitted. Okay? So it's not
like there's a תקנה and the circumstances have changed. Okay? The reality
of it being one קדושה was the natural outgrowth of not accepting
the witnesses. So once that stopped, then that natural outgrowth stopped being
the reality and it became two קדושות. Okay? Is that pretty clear
to people what's being said here? Is everybody already lost? Okay, I'm
detecting by the quiet and that you're keeping your heads down that
you are lost.
Basically, let me just try to sum that whole point up. Okay,
the question is once, when again, when
you cannot accept witnesses on the first day of ראש השנה Rosh
Hashana because of a, because of a תקנה, right? So there were
elements of non-ספק safek. that still had times when you weren't in
doubt and you still had two days ראש השנה. That reality of
not accepting witnesses created a reality of one קדושה. So the question,
and that means born on one day forbidden on the next. So
the question is once you, that reality changed and you could start
accepting witnesses, right? Does that now switch it to be two קדושות?
And if the argument is no, then the question is why not?
Because logically it should switch because it's no longer that reality of
that תקנה. So one answer was, well, in חוץ לארץ it remains
the way it was because the practice never shifted. Now the answer
we're trying to say is no, that reality of one קדושה was
its own תקנה. So even though the issue about the witnesses shifted,
that reality did not change. That's the idea you would need another
act of legislation to retract it. To which אביי's retort is, it
wasn't like there was a legislation to make it one קדושה. That
was a reality that emerged from the fact that the witnesses were
not accepted. Once the witnesses began to be accepted, then that emergent
reality has shifted and therefore should be permitted. Logically it should be
two קדושות, says אביי, and not one קדושה. That is not a
sufficient explanation of why the two days ראש השנה are one קדושה.
Things remain the same? They shouldn't. It was emergent from the witness
reality and that reality has shifted. You had a
question, Jonathan?
The issue's gonna revolve around the confusion from year to year, right?
The issue's going to revolve around the confusion from, I'm not sure
what you're...
Year to year. One year you'll say...
Yes, one year one year might be the first day and the
next year it'll be the second day and there's a reality of
ספק. safek Correct, there's a reality of ספק. safek, Okay.
We did it last year so why can't we do it this
year, but this year's different than last
year.
Yes. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. רב אדא בר אהבה
ותרוייהו מבי כלוחי אמרי, Rav Adda bar Ahava v'tarvaihu mibei kluchei amri,
so the two of them from the house of כלוחי Kluchei say,
אף מדרשת רבי יוחנן בן זכאי ואילך ביצה אסורה, af midirshat Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai ve'eilech beitzi asura, even though now the reality is
witnesses could be accepted, the egg remains forbidden, meaning it remains one
קדושה. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? מהרה יבנה בית המקדש, Mehera yibaneh Beit
Hamikdash, oh
this is what you
were saying Jonathan, maybe because God willing the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash will be
rebuilt quickly, ויאמרו veyomru and people will say, אשתקד מי לא אכלנו
ביצה ביום טוב שני? ishtakad milo achlanu beitzi b'yom tov sheini?
Look, last year when it was born on day one, we ate
it on day two. השתא נמי ניכול, Hashta nami neichol, let's do
the same now. ולא ידעי Veloyadi and they won't know דאשתקד שתי
קדושות הן. de'ishtakad shei kedushos hein. When there was no בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash we accepted witnesses the whole day and that created a
reality of ספק safek. and that created
שתי קדושות. Shte Kedushot. והשתא קדושה אחת היא. V'hashta kedusha achas hi.
There's the reality of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. there's the reality
that we won't accept witnesses, therefore there's an element of תקנה and
therefore it's one קדושה. So because you don't want people to make
that mistake, we're going to keep it as one קדושה even though
it should logically be two. Okay, which is basically saying as opposed
to רבא Rava that says we would need to retract it and
we're stuck with it, here saying we're not stuck with it, but
we proactively chose to be stuck with it, we proactively chose to
continue the practice of one קדושה to continue that reality for, you
know, what would be in the future. So the גמרא says: אי
הכי עדות נמי לא נקבל. ee hachi eidus nami lo nekabel. So
how could we allow to accept witnesses? Let's be afraid. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? Let's have the same concern. מהרה יבנה בית המקדש ויאמרו
אשתקד מי לא קבלנו עדות החדש כל היום כולו? Mehera yibaneh Beis
Hamikdash veyomru ishtakad milo kibalnu eidus hachodesh kol hayom kulo? Look, last
year we accepted עדות the whole day. השתא נמי נקבל. Hashta nami
nekabel. So now this year let's do the same. If you're worried
about what will happen when the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. gets rebuilt,
how did you allow a shift in the whole idea of accepting
witnesses? You shouldn't allow witnesses to be accepted because that will be
a changed הלכה when the בית המקדש is rebuilt. So the גמרא
says: הכי השתא? Hachi hashta? What type of a question is that?
התם Hatam over there, עדות מסורה לבית דין. eidus mesura l'veit din.
There, בית דין is the one that accepts witnesses. בית דין isn't
going to make that obvious mistake of oh last year we accepted
the whole... בית דין will know! There's a בית המקדש now and
you don't accept witnesses from מנחה time onward. So that we don't,
that we're able to change because we can trust בית דין to
know the הלכה. But ביצה לכל מסורה. beitza l'chol mesura. The egg,
that's every farmer. Every farmer's got
eggs! So they'll make mistakes. So we have to maintain שתי קדושות.
So again, the question is now that we accept witnesses the whole
day and there's a reality of ספק, why not say שתי קדושות?
And the answer why do we say one קדושה, and the answers
that we have are either we're stuck with the past, just naturally,
we would need to legislate it out, or that no, proactively we
decided to keep the past reality because of the question of the
future building of the בית המקדש. Okay, so that's the so that's
right now but explaining the idea of one קדושה. Now let's continue,
finish this up.
Where was it? רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא says, אף מדרשת רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי ואילך ביצה אסורה. af midirshat Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai
ve'eilech beitzi asura. Everybody is saying this idea. Even now that we
accept witnesses, the idea is the egg is forbidden, one קדושה. Why?
מי לא מודה רבי יוחנן בן זכאי שאם באו עדים מן המנחה
ולמעלה שנוהגים אותו היום קדש ולמחר קדש? Mi lo modeh Rabbi Yochanan
ben Zakkai she'im ba'u eidim min hamincha u'l'ma'ala she'nohagim oto yom kodesh
u'l'machar kodesh? This very funny phrase, you know, what that means. רש"י
and תוספות both struggle to explain it, but basically it says: look,
רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, you know, himself would
say that that when the עדים came from מנחה time onward that
you continue the day בקדושה. bikdusha. Okay, that's very nice. But what
does that mean? So רש"י saying like this. No, no. Even when
רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai said you can now
accept witnesses, he never, he kept the reality, he would not have
changed the reality of קדושה אחת. Kedusha Achat There was a reality
in place that you would always have, you know, that you would
have two days יום טוב when the witnesses came later even though,
right, you knew and there was no longer a doubt and so
on, that was when there was a בית המקדש. רבי יוחנן בן
זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai changed the reality of accepting witnesses, but
sort of רבא's saying, yeah, but it's obvious he wouldn't have changed
the reality of one קדושה. Now the question is like why is
it obvious? Well, it's obvious. It's obvious to רבא. So so now
again, why did it not shift from one קדושה to שתי קדושות?
We have three reasons. Either we were stuck with the old תקנה
because we didn't legislate it out, or two, we proactively made a
new תקנה to keep the idea of קדושה אחת Kedusha Achat. because
of מהרה יבנה, Mehera Yibaneh, or what רבא is saying, which is
I think that רבן יוחנן בן זכאי sort of used a scalpel
and when he was changing the issue of accepting witnesses, he was
leaving aside and untouched and maintaining the idea of קדושה אחת. Kedusha
Achat So three different explanations, but we're basically keeping the reality of
קדושה אחת Kedusha Achat even now that we can accept witnesses. And
now the גמרא wraps up and says ואמר רבא הלכתא כוותיה דרב
בהני תלת בין לקולא בין לחומרא. VeAmar Rava Hilchata Kevatei DeRav BeHani
Telat Bein LeKula Bein LeChumra. We rule like רב in these three
cases, whether leniency or strictly. I want to remind you what the
three cases are. One was יום טוב and שבת Shabbat and if
it's born on one day the egg is it מותר muttar on
the next, and there רב was strict and רב said that if
it's born on שבת Shabbat it's אסור assur on יום טוב if
they're back to back or born on יום טוב it remains אסור
assur on שבת. Shabbat. That actually, somewhat ironically, he treated as קדושה
אחת Kedusha Achat or the גמרא said maybe because of הכנה דרבה.
Hachana DeRabba. So there we're strict. The other case was two days
of a normal two days of יום טוב of חוצה לארץ Chutza
La'Aretz where if it's born on one day it's permitted on the
second because that's based on ספק. That's שתי קדושות. There we also
פסקן pasken like רב leniently. And the third case is our case
of ראש השנה that even after the תקנה of רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי it remains קדושה אחת Kedusha Achat and therefore born on one
day forbidden on the next, but as I said a lot of
other implications of קדושה אחת Kedusha Achat. like saying שהחיינו and other
types of things. The last thing I need to say is we
finish this גמרא and you're saying okay fine what I conclude is
when in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. they have two days because the
עדים come, the עדים don't come till the next day, it has
the reality of קדושה אחת. Kedusha Achat But it never says anywhere
that you have to have two days in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael.
and when the witnesses came earlier, it sounds like you would keep
one day. It's only a question of what would be the reality
when they came the second day, would it be קדושה אחת Kedusha
Achat or שתי קדושות. Nevertheless the רי"ף Riff quotes this whole גמרא
and ends by saying and therefore we keep two days of ראש
השנה all the time even in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael And he
somehow understands that the conclusion that they maintain קדושה אחת Kedusha Achat.
and we maintain that you know for all the various reasons that
were said but somehow we maintain that old תקנה also means that
we always do two days even in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael It's
fascinating to note that that was not so clear, that the בעל
המאור Baal HaMaor and other ראשונים Rishonim argued on the רי"ף Riff
and said in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. one day ראש השנה, not
two days ראש השנה as you know when the witnesses came, come
you know on the first day or if it's based on a
calendar then when it's supposed to be you know on the 30th
day of אלול Elul which is pretty much every year because אלול
Elul is never has never had 30 days. If it's an early
ראש השנה then it's always going to be one day ראש השנה.
So there actually is a debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. The idea
that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they always keep two days is
not in the גמרא. It's a debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Yes.
Is it theoretical? Is it just theoretical? Or is it possible logically
to go being one day of ראש השנה but of course we
do two days of ראש השנה even today?
No, what these other ראשונים Rishonim are saying is the רי"ף Riff
is wrong. In practice you keep one day of ראש השנה in
ארץ ישראל. Now in our what we know is this is the
only holiday that they keep in ארץ ישראל two days and they
treat it as קדושה אחת. Kedusha Achat Somehow an understanding of קדושה
אחת Kedusha Achat. means and not only when it's two days but
you always keep two days as קדושה אחת. But yeah it's a
big shocker to learn that that's not in the גמרא and according
to a number of ראשונים Rishonim you basically do one day of
ראש השנה. Yes.
What about the משנה that says that you know ביצה sometimes seven
eight nine ten and that implies two days of ראש השנה?
When there are two days of ראש השנה. But not but there
could be years.
The רי"ף Riff is saying there's always two days.
Sorry, those who argue on the רי"ף Riff are
saying sometimes it's two days when the witnesses come late, I mean
not come late, when the witnesses come on day two which you
know so then you kept the whole first day because it might
have wound up being ראש השנה and you keep you know and
then you keep the second day. So when the witnesses come on
day two there are two days but when the witnesses came on
day one there's one day. I know it's a shock.